Hello and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be looking
at molecular orbital theory.
Now what molecular orbital theory is
essentially an extension of the idea
behind hybridization, where we get
into a more realistic interpretation
of how the atoms function.
So this is an even more advanced method.
So what MO theory does is essentially
it's, it's describing the distribution
of electrons between molecules.
Now this is very similar to what
we've always kind of imagined when
we were talking about orbitals and
electron configuration, where before
we thought electrons were always
surrounded by atoms, and we were able
to describe that using atomic orbitals.
Now, up until this point, we
should know a few different things.
Before kind of continuing with this
video, uh, you should have really good
knowledge of Lewis structures, electron
pair geometry, molecular geometries,
so everything that's vesper oriented.
I would recommend knowing a little
bit about Val Bond theory and
hybridization in that viewpoint versus
molecular orbital theory, which is
a little bit of a different way of
approaching the same type of problem.
And we're gonna be trying to, we're
gonna be explaining some bonding
properties that have been seen before.
So one thing is like, where
does this kind of come up?
Well, let's say if we start something
small, let's say with oxygen.
If you're to look at this
molecule, well, oxygen seems
to be something normal, right?
We need it to be, to stay alive.
If I were to actually kind of go
through and draw the diagrams behind
this, especially after looking at
the entire concept of hybridization,
well, first thing is if I were to
kind of look at that, well, when these
molecules bond together, they're gonna
rearrange their electrons through
a process known as hybridization.
Which we've talked about, uh, previously,
is the whole idea here is that we're
gonna try to lower energy levels.
So that way they can bond together.
Now when this happens, well these
different guys, they will, they
will bond, they're gonna make a
couple different bonds as a result.
Meaning we'll have a Sigma single bond
that's gonna form, but we also have
that double bond two in the structure.
So then we're gonna have this interaction
between the parallel, uh, P orbitals on
hybridized p orbitals to make a Pi bond.
So sigma and Pi together
make a double bond Now.
That's great.
That's what we learned all about.
Balanced bond theory.
The thing is, there's something
that's still not able to be explained,
which is essentially when you run
oxygen as a liquid through a magnetic
field, it shows magnetic properties.
And one of the things as
well, why would it do that?
Why don't we show this?
And let's say we're run two
different molecules through a magnet.
So what we have is a very cooled
liquid nitrogen, and we're going
to be pouring that through a magnet
now as expected nitrogen gas.
We see that it does not connect
to the magnets on both sides of
this, so there's nothing happening.
The second that I put liquid
oxygen over these magnets.
Now, if we kinda look really closely,
you see that it's fusing to the
magnets, that it's sticking oxygen.
That's magnetic.
What?
How come we don't see oxygen
magnetizing to all the metals around us?
How is that possible?
Right?
There's nothing that we kind of
have to explain that at the moment.
However, there was a concept we
did mention not that long ago,
which was all about the idea of
param magnetism and DM magnetism.
Para was all about that.
Whenever molecules had unpaired electrons,
they were attracted to electrons.
However, looking at my diagram,
especially once I have everything
bonded, there are no unpaired
electrons within the molecule itself.
However, oxygen actually does
have two unpaired electrons.
Where are they?
I don't see them.
Anywhere in the hybridization
picture that we've discussed.
So this is a problem that means that
hybridization is missing some kind
of key component to it that is not
actually able to describe everything.
So we're gonna be comparing
when something's paramagnetic
or diamagnetic by learning about
MO theory and when this works.
So just as a reminder, diamagnetic was
whenever you had all paired electrons,
and that's what oxygen looks like.
So where do these two unpaired
electrons I claim are coming from?
Let's dive into the theory.
First thing is, is essentially
trying to compare the different
theories that we've been talking
about in terms of general chemistry.
The first one that everybody
learns about is valence bond
theory, which is hybridization.
Let's talk about that first, and then
we'll go into what the differences
are with molecular orbital theory.
So when we talked about hybridization,
the entire idea with this one is
essentially considered electrons localized
in bonds between individual atoms.
Whenever these bonds were created, it
was mainly due to overlap of different
atomic orbitals and hybrid orbitals.
When this happened, essentially whenever
you had a overlap of hybrid with atomic
or hybrid and hybrid, we made sigma bonds.
Whenever it was the atomic orbitals
interacting with each other, we
had PI bonds that were making.
Now, why is that?
Something that was great is that it
gave us the ability to actually explain
the why for how vesper structures work.
Meaning it predicts molecular shape by
determining where most likely the regions
of electron density are a K steric number.
So it gives us a good thought process.
One downfall to this is that it
essentially says that electrons are
localized, meaning they're in one spot.
So we need a ton of structure to
describe resonance, which the whole
idea of resonance is that multiple
structures exist all at the same time.
Bond order changes as a result, so it
doesn't really do its best in explaining.
All pictures, especially being that
resonance is a big part of how our
body functions, especially if you kind
of think of it in terms of like the
peptide bonds and for a lot of different
structures that we see in time in terms
of like the pharmaceutical industry.
So when we're comparing this,
so let's say molecular orbital
theory, well what's the difference?
Well, this theory kind
of tweaks that process.
What if instead I say, okay, let's
say the electrons are delocalized
throughout the molecule, whereas
all of the atomic orbitals are
working together all at one time.
So when that happens, the atomic
orbitals are gonna instead
create molecular orbitals.
So if I have multiple atoms all in this
molecule, they're all working together
to create a, an entirely new orbital.
So valance bond theory was all
about one single atom hybridizing.
Moleculars, the whole molecule is
changing to make different orbitals.
Now, when this happens, the or, those
atomic orbitals are going to interact.
To make what we call bonding and
anti-bonding interactions, which
are gonna be different types of
orbitals that are gonna be forming.
Now, what this is gonna be
used for is to help us predict
the arrangements of electrons.
So not just the structure, but exactly
where are, where's the probability
of these electrons being located when
we try to think of quantum mechanics.
So it's gonna give us a, uh,
essentially us assuming where
the lowest energy possibility is.
So that way we can get an idea of
what the orbital picture looks like,
so we can know how a molecule truly
behaves on the electronic level.
So let's take a look at both of these.
So the first thing when we get to MO
theory is that the whole idea behind
this is that we need to calculate
the orbitals for the entire molecule.
But don't worry, there's no math at this
one for at least for general chemistry.
This is something that's generally
reserved for research in institutes
or very high level graduate students
who are trying to, you know, hit
their head against the wall a little
bit to understand all the basics.
It can be some done in general
chemistry, but usually it's on
a very, very simplistic level.
So where does this all come from?
Well, it's whole idea is that
if you, what we're trying to do
is solve the Stroger equation.
And the thing is with that
is that it's actually pretty
much impossible to solve it.
Exactly.
Alls we can do is try to make an
approximation because the electrons are
moving so fast, it's, it's, there's too
much uncertainty for us to know exactly
where they located at a given time.
So when we're trying to look at this
thing, we can approximate what the
wave function is, meaning we can try to
figure out an idea of what the shape is
or where the electrons most likely are.
So what is this kind of analogous
to here is that electrons around
these atoms are limited to
discrete quantized energy levels.
So it's a, it's the same kind of
idea in the mo molecular picture too.
The only difference is that, well,
once we kind of assume that all these
atomic orbitals are working together.
Is that we can actually figure out where
the electrons are most likely located in
the mul, a molecular orbital between this.
So if we square a wave function, we can
figure out the probability and plot it
of most likely where these things are.
Keep in mind when we're doing this,
it's gonna be very similar to electron
configuration, meaning it's still gonna
follow the poly exclusion principle.
The off bowel principle where we start
with lowest energy first and fill up
and we'll still do our, um, huns roll
where we do degenerate orbitals as well.
So it's almost the exact same
thing as what we've been doing
before, but just some different
symbols with sigma and Pi bonds.
So let's dive a little farther.
The first thing is, is
where's all this coming from?
So whenever we're looking at these,
it's all talking about what we call the
linear combination of atomic orbitals.
L-C-A-O for short, which
is a more common acronym.
So whenever we talk about this, in a
sense, it's just adding up all the,
or the atomic orbitals together to
create the all the molecular orbitals.
So say for example, if I have two atomic
orbitals going in, I'm going to end up
having two molecular orbitals coming out.
Now the difference between valance bond
theory was, is that valance bond theory
only combined the orbitals of one atom.
This is talking about two or
three or four combining together
to make a giant molecule.
In our case, we're just gonna stick
with two just to make it easy.
'cause we're, we're beginners.
Right?
We're just starting off to understand.
So the whole idea of where this comes from
is actually based on how waves worked.
So if you kind of thought of a wave, well,
if they were in the phase with each other,
so both starting at the exact same point
like I have here on the left hand side,
they would construct or add up together.
Or if I had them slightly out of
phase with one another, where one of
'em is down, the other one's up, they
will deconstruct with one another.
So with the same idea here,
orbitals do the same thing.
Orbitals can be in phase or they can
also be out of phase, and it's all
based on where the electron is located
in a given part of that orbital.
So if it's in one region, it's in phase.
If it's in another region,
it's more out of phase.
So there's different areas where most
likely it's going to be at one time.
Right.
It's almost like a coin flip.
So when we're trying to try to
figure out where exactly is it?
Well, as a result of this is we can
create two different types of orbitals
every time two atomic orbitals interact.
So remember two atomic orbitals, we're
gonna get two molecular orbitals.
So every time, let's say you have s and
s interact, what you're gonna get is one
orbital is going to be a bonding orbital,
and the other one's gonna be anti-bonding.
Now, what's the difference?
Does that mean one doesn't even interact?
Not entirely.
It's just a more of a vernacular word
that's being chose by the community.
So the whole idea here was whenever
we have bonding, is that this is the
lower energy orbital, meaning that
it's gonna have the two nucleon.
They're gonna be interacting together
and it's essentially like making
a sigma bond or a Pi bond that's
interacting directly with that.
It's gonna have a lot more electron
density, it's gonna be lower energy.
Very, very stable.
Whereas whenever we have
anti-bonding, well this is one that
is a little bit higher in energy.
It's a little more unstable.
It's actually kind of working against
the nuclei being in the ultimate place.
So it's kind of like a checks
and balance type of system.
It's like one of 'em
is working really well.
The other one tends to work a little bit
outta character, a little outta sync.
So it's destabilize it.
So it's a give intake, right?
You can't just have a million bonds
form in between the two atoms.
It's a low energy and a high energy.
So what does this look
like in terms of a picture?
Well, if we're talking about two
different nuclei, so let's say I have
atom one on my left, and then atom two
in green, so purple and green here.
So both of them have an S orbital
that are interacting with each other.
What exactly is gonna happen?
When they interact well, if they're
both interacting on this axis for
the nuclei, ir one orbital is going
to end up adding together, right?
So creating our sigma bond in the bonding
orbital, and then being that if we
started with two atomic orbitals, well
we must have another orbital as well.
So we're also gonna create an
anti-bonding orbital where they're
out of phase with each other.
So we're always gonna have two going in.
Then we'll have two coming out.
So we have a higher energy,
the anti-bonding, and then
the lower energy bonding.
Now with this, right, we
can see they're both sigma.
So Sigma S, 'cause we're
talking about the S orbital.
The way that we tell the
difference is sigma without,
with a star and without a star.
So when it has a star next to
it, that means anti-bonding.
It's really high energy where
wherever we have it, without one
that's telling you it's bonding.
And this can happen with different
orbitals as well, not just s. So
we can go a little bit farther.
We can do it with p orbitals
too, because they can also
interact on the same axis too.
So let's say if we're think of the
same thing, well, if I have PX and PX
going together, so two atomic orbitals,
well, how many molecular orbitals
do you think are gonna come out?
And if you guess the
right, it's gonna be two.
Right?
So once again, we're gonna have
a bonding and an anti-bonding.
So when they're head to head or
overlapping, just like hybridization.
That's when we make the sigma bonds.
So the way to kind of tell when it's
bonding, you can kind of see the
over the overlap between the orbital,
like right in the middle here.
We can see all that really connecting
with each other, where whenever the
orbitals ended up being out of phase, they
end up not matching in terms of color.
They can't actually create a, a
stable bond, so it's very high energy.
Let's see what other types we had.
So we had sigma, we also had pi.
Let's look at the other.
But whenever we had PI bonds, the
whole thing about these is that
they had to be parallel with one
another, so facing each other.
So when we had that parallel orbital
connecting, well, once again, let's say if
I were to look at the PY and PY together
at the top two orbitals are going in.
How many need to come out?
It's gonna be two.
Same thing with pz, right?
They're both in line with each other, or
sorry, it's more in line this way, right?
We can see them together, so it's
gonna be the same general idea.
So let's look.
So with these, right, they each
make two sets of different orbitals.
So we can see like one, almost looks
like a butterfly with alternating wings.
Then the other two, when they
overlap and merge together, it helps
create that delocalized Pi bond that
goes between two individual atoms.
So just to kind of like think about that.
Well, where are the atoms?
Well, let's say if the atom would
be like kind of right in the
middle of each of these orbitals.
So where I'm putting these red dots.
So it'd be like where the nuclei are
in are in reference to one another.
So it's all about like kinda where, where
are they in the different structures?
We're always gonna have two
individual orbitals making two others.
So let's go through some examples of when
this is possible, because I'm sure by
now it's a little confusing to follow.
When can we make each one
of these different orbitals?
The whole idea here is
when we're looking at them.
So if you're given a pair of orbitals,
you're just trying to figure out,
well, can they form and can they not?
Well, what could we make,
if you remember right?
Well, we had sigma.
PI right from hybridization.
So Sigma was all about overlap,
and PI was about being parallel.
Now, the only difference here, it's,
well, what kind of orbital can it make?
Can it be sigma bonding, Pi
bonding with or, or anti-bonding?
Or maybe it's even possible where it
doesn't make a bond at all, right?
So if it doesn't fit either
definitions, that's possible too.
So let's say if I were to look at
this first one, some, I'm adding
together two three PX orbitals.
So we see them over here on the left
hand side, and the whole idea here
as well, they're facing each other.
So it says facing only.
So being that they're facing each
other, these two orbitals are going
to come together and we can see
that they're adding together, right?
They have the exact same
color as one another.
So what type of orbital do you
think they're gonna be being that
they're gonna be overlapping?
Well, the first thing is, is, well,
it's definitely gonna be Sigma.
Is it bonding or anti-bonding?
Well, it's gonna end up forming
one where they have a ton of
overlap as a result, right?
So being that they have that
overlap, how can we label that?
Well, that's going to be a Sigma Bond.
And to be more specific, we could say,
Hey, that Sigma three PX being that
they were the ones that were forming
that individual orbital that are there.
So we can, we can put that in our details.
Now for the next one, it says, we have px.
And PY coming together.
So how about this one?
Well, if I've tried to overlap
them with the side, well before,
whenever we talked about overlap,
they were always on the same axis,
and PI was always on parallel AEs.
So it doesn't really match
either of our definitions.
So what's gonna happen here?
This is when we're gonna make no
bond, being that it doesn't match
them on the same or parallel.
So it's either together.
Or take or tear it together, right?
It's one or the other.
So what about this one?
So this last one, okay,
they're both parallel.
So what does that tell us?
Well, it's definitely Pi.
Are they in phase with one another?
Well, if we look at the colors, we can
see that they're opposite of one another.
So what does that mean?
Is that they're gonna be out
of phase with one another.
So what should this make is it should
be PI three PY based on the original
orbitals we were starting with.
So if we were to try to draw that
the best we can, we should see those
butterfly wings that we had previously.
And this is usually information that
you're always given is what orbitals
you're starting with and you try to
predict, okay, well which one is it?
Or you're just filling in the different
or different orbitals as well.
So this is kind of one of those ideas
of just how does this whole thing work?
So this is the theory
behind it or the basic idea.
So where exactly can we apply this?
Well, the whole concept with this thing
is that we usually will fill in molecular
orbital diagrams to show this meaning
that we're going to be trying to see how
are all the different electrons gonna
be filling in, starting at the lowest,
using the alpha bowel principle, and
then filling it all the way up, um,
to, to whatever the highest levels are.
And that's where we can get the param
magnetism and dia magnetism that
we've seen in the video from before.
So that's where the second
part video is gonna come in.
Where it's gonna go to, how to fill
in, uh, molecular orbital diagrams.
So that will be the, the next video to try
to cut this up a little bit for everybody.
Uh, alright, let's thank you so much
for listening and I'll see you guys
in the next video for the molecular
orbital diagrams, which will go mainly
through practice problems and examples.
Okay, see you y'all soon.
Bye.